Guide to the Russian State Military Archives Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- German-Soviet Military Cooperation, 1918-1934; Series I
  - Memo report N° 21/ss. from Baranov to Frunze, 1925 June 16; 84 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Memo report N° 21/ss. from Baranov to Frunze on the candidacy of VVS workers to be sent on an official trip to Germany. Original.
  - Report N° 5969 from M.I. Frumkin to the STO USSR, 1925 July 8; 85 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Report N° 5969 from M.I. Frumkin, Dep. Narkom of Foreign Trade, to the STO USSR on Derutra, a Russian-German association with limited liability.
  - Resolution of the STO USSR on "Derutra", 1925 June 11; 86 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Resolution of the STO USSR for a report by the Narkom of Foreign Trade of the USSR on the Russian storage and transport association "Derutra". Certified copy.
  - Report on the point of view of the German government, 1925 July 20; 87 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Report, sent to M.V. Frunze, on the point of view of the German government on a Note from the Entente concerning German aeronautics and the significance of the Soviet market for the German aviation industry. Certified copy.
  - Memorandum N° 8002/s., 1925 July 31; 88 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Memorandum N° 8002/s. from the Directorate of the Military Air Forces to the Legal-Statistical Department of the Main Directorate of the Red Army on the question of the assignment of a Glavkontsesskom credit of 1 million rubles for Junkers. Original.
  - Memorandum N° 34515s. from Khaskin to Baranov, 1925 August 7; 89 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Memorandum N° 34515s. from Khaskin, the temporary head of the Military Finance Directorate, to Baranov on agreement with a scheme of the STO USSR to allot a subsidy to Junkers for construction work. Original.
  - Letter from P.N. Lunev to M.V. Frunze, 1925 August 14; 90 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letter from P.N. Lunev, the military attache in Germany, to M.V. Frunze on the inspection by him of the Hertz optical factory and radio-telegraph equipment used by the Reichswehr. Certified copy.
  - Letter from P.N. Lunev to M.V. Frunze, 1925 August 18; 91 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letter from P.N. Lunev to M.V. Frunze on the take-off of a Junkers A-20 airplane for a connection with Lipetsk, on the departure to Moscow of the representative of the firm Telefunken and on [his] trip to Vienna. Certified copy.
  - Letter from P.N. Lunev to M.V. Frunze, 1925 August 10; 92 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letter from P.N. Lunev to M.V. Frunze with information on German officers travelling to maneuvers in the USSR and on the participation of Soviet commanders in the Reichswehr's general maneuvers, on business relations with the German firms Junkers and Mayer. Certified copy.
  - Survey of international relations in the Locarno period, 1925 October 20; 93 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Survey of international relations in the Locarno period and on the position of the German delegation during talks with the allies' representatives. Copy.
  - Survey of the international situation before and after Locarno Conference, 1925 October 21; 94 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Survey of the international situation before and after the Locarno Conference and striving by the German government for a decentralization of trade with the USSR. Copy.
  - Survey of the international situation after the Locarno Conference, 1925 October 28; 95 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Survey of the international situation after the Locarno Conference, of Germany's political and economic state and of the tactics of the German government and the opposition. Certified copy.
  - Memo report from the Directorate of the VVS to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1925 November 12; 96 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Memo report from the concessionary department of the Directorate of the VVS to K.Ye. Voroshilov, Chairman of the RVS USSR on the contract with Junkers; with attached information on the main disagreements between the drafts of the contract from the company and from Glavkontsesskom. Certified copy.
  - Memo report from Baranov to Voroshilov, 1925 November 4; 97 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Memo report from Baranov to Voroshilov on the possibility of organizing production of metal airplanes at Junker's factory with the participation of Soviet specialists. Original.
  - Report N° 96 from Voroshilov, 1925 January 24; 98 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Report N° 96 from Voroshilov on the status of affairs with the airplane-building concessionary joint-stock company Junkers for the period 1924-1925 and the necessity for speeding up a decision on the contract with them. Copy.
  - Account of the official trip to Germany of I.P. Grave, 1925; 99 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Account of the official trip to Germany of I.P. Grave, professor at the Military-Technical Academy. Copy.
  - Memo report from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo, 1926 March 1; 100 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Memo report from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo on the necessity for abrogating the concessionary contract with Junkers, in view of their non-fulfillment of the commitments that they had made.
  - Report from R.A. Muklevich to L.D. Trotskii, 1926 March 10; 101 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Report from R.A. Muklevich, Dep. Chief of the VVS of the Red Army, to L.D. Trotskii on the reasons for the abrogation of the contract with Junkers. Certified copy.
  - Letter from Ya.I. Alksnis to I.S. Unshlikht, 1926 March 13; 102 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Letter from Ya.I. Alksnis to I.S. Unshlikht on the contract with Junkers. Original.
  - Memo report from I.S. Unshlikht to the Politburo, 1926 April 10; 103 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Memo report from I.S. Unshlikht to the Politburo on the course of the talks with the Reichswehr.
  - Memo report from I.A. Khalepskii on the talks with Telefunken, 1926 April 14; 104 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Memo report from I.A. Khalepskii, Chief of the Military-Technical Directorate on the talks with Telefunken, Siemens and Zeiss.
  - Protocol on 12 bombers ordered from Junkers, 1926 May 29; 105 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Protocol of a meeting on the contract for 12 bombers ordered from Junkers.
  - Record of talks of I.S. Unshlikht with von Schlieben and Niedermeyer, 1926 June 14; 106 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Record of talks of I.S. Unshlikht with von Schlieben and Niedermeyer on the course of the collaboration.
  - Report from V.I. Zof to the RVS, 1926 June 14; 107 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Report from V.I. Zof, Chief and Commissar of the Naval Forces of the Red Army, to the RVS on a visit of Leningrad and Baltflot with foreign representatives.
  - Declaration from Baranov to Junkers' representatives, 1926 June 15; 108 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Declaration from Baranov to Junkers' representatives on willingness for collaboration with the firm and the necessity for speeding up a decision on technical matters. Certified copy.
  - Report N° 161/ms. from V.I. Zof, 1926 June 16; 109 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Report N° 161/ms. from V.I. Zof on the reception of German representatives Spindler and Koch. Copy.
  - Conclusion No. 16/ss. from Baranov, 1926 June 26; 110 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Conclusion No. 16/ss. from Baranov on the necessity for liquidating Junkers concession. Original.
  - Information No. 926s. from S.A. Mezheninov, 1926 June 26; 111 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Information No. 926s. from S.A. Mezheninov, assistant in the VVS on the Junkers affair. Certified Copy.
  - Summary on liquidation of contractual relations with Junkers, 1926 July 28; 112 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Summary of the most important questions connected with the liquidation of contractual relations with Junkers. Copy.
  - Letter form Unterman, 1926 November 25; 113 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Letter from Unterman on the abrogation of the contract with Bersol'.
  - Contract on the creation of Deruluft, 1927 January 12; 114 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Contract on the creation of a joint-stock Russian-German company Deruluft. Certified copy.
  - Memo report of the Junkers airplane-building factory, 1927 January 22; 115 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Memo report from the representative of the Junkers airplane-building factory to the Main Concessionary Committee in the SNK USSR on the drawing-up of an agreement concerning the abrogation of contracts. Translated from German.
  - Report from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo I.V. Stalin, 1927 January 28; 116 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Report from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo I.V. Stalin on the speeding up of the abrogation of the contract for the delivery of bombers with the German firm Junkers, in connection with the systematic non-fulfillment of their contractual obligations. Copy.
  - Information on talks with Junkers, 1927 February 3; 117 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Information on talks with Junkers, prepared by S.A. Mezheninov, the Assistant Chief of the UVVS of the Red Army. Original.
  - Report form Krasil'nikov and Svechnikov, 1927 February 11; 118 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Report from Krasil'nikov and Svechnikov, instructors at the Frunze military Academy, to Eideman, Chief of the Academy, on a trip to Germany. Copy.
  - Memorandum No. 010238 from S.S. Yoffe to I.P. Tovstukh, 1927 February 14; 119 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Memorandum No. 010238 from S.S. Yoffe, Secretary of the Narkomvoenmor, to I.P. Tovstukh, Head of the Secret Department of the TsK VKP(b). Certified Copy.
  - Letter No. 532 from I.S. Unshlikht to Baranov, 1927 March 5; 120 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter No. 532 from I.S. Unshlikht to Baranov on the conclusion of a contract with a German firm for the acquisition of 100 BMW-VI motors. Certified copy.
  - Protocol on liquidation of Bersol', 1927 April 5; 121 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Protocol from the general meeting of the stockholders and founders of the Russian-German joint-stock company Bersol' on its liquidation with the attendance of I.S. Unshlikht. Certified copy.
  - Letter N° 021/ss. from S.S. Yoffe to the medical commission of the TsK VKP(b), 1927 October 31; 122 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter N° 021/ss. from S.S. Yoffe to the medical commission of the TsK VKP(b) on the assigning of the means for Voroshilov's medical treatment. Certified copy.
  - Memo report N° 0427381/ss. from Ya.K. Berzin to I.S. Unshlikht, 1927 October 31; 123 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Memo report N° 0427381/ss. from Ya.K. Berzin, Chief of the 4th Directorate of the Red Army Staff, to I.S. Unshlikht, Dep. Chairman of the RVS USSR on the official trip of IP. Uborevich to Germany. Certified copy.
  - Survey "German Press on the Military Danger and on the USSR and on the VKP(b)", Circa 1927 June - November 14; 124 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Survey of foreign press given to Voroshilov's secretariat by Ye.V. Stasov "German Press on the Military Danger, on the USSR and on the VKP(b)". (Document is dated by its contents, since L.D. Trotskii was put out of the party at the 15th Party Congress (Dec. 1927) and out of the Comintern at the 9th Plenum of the Comintern Executive Committee, formed 9-25 Feb. 1928). Copy.
  - Letter N° 054/ss. from K.Ye. Voroshilov to Lunev, 1927 December 2; 125 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter N° 054/ss. from K.Ye. Voroshilov to Lunev, the military attache in Germany on the necessity for bettering information on the current work. Copy.
  - Letter N° 055/ss. from K.Ye. Voroshilov to G.V. Chicherin, 1927 December 2; 126 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter N° 055/ss. from K.Ye. Voroshilov to G.V. Chicherin on the necessity to receive from the German Ministry of Foreign Affairs pennission for I.P. Uborevich to remain in Germany for a longer period of time. Certified copy.
  - Letter N° 077/ss. from Voroshilov to Chicherin, 1927 December 16; 127 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter N° 077/ss. from Voroshilov to Chicherin on the lengthening of I.P. Uborevich's stay in Germany. Certified copy.
  - Report from A.I. Mikoyan to commission on economic talks with Germany, 1928 January 29; 128 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Report from A.I. Mikoyan, the Narkom of Foreign Trade of the USSR, to the members of a commission dealing with economic talks with Germany on the "large program" of economic collaboration. Original.
  - Note N° 0183 from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo I.V. Stalin, 1928 February 28; 129 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Note N° 0183 from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo I.V. Stalin with a request (with a proposal) to consider joint official trips of commanders of the Red Army and the Reichswehr to maneuvers. Copy.
  - Protocol of a meeting of a Politburo commission on economic talks with Germany, 1928 February 29; 130 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Protocol of a meeting of a Politburo commission on economic talks with Germany; with a resolution on the continuation of the realization of the "large program" of collaboration. Copy.
  - Letter N° 0215s/s. from K.Ye. Voroshilov to N.N. Krestinskii, 1928 March; 131 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Letter N° 0215s/s. from K.Ye. Voroshilov to N.N. Krestinskii, the ambassador to Germany, regarding the reception of German officers and the dispatching of Soviet commanders to Germany on maneuvers and exercises. Copy.
  - Report N° 4007041 from I.A. Khalepskii to I.S. Unshlikht, 1928 May 16; 132 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Report N° 4007041 from I.A. Khalepskii to I.S. Unshlikht on the official trip to Germany. Original.
  - Note N° 0311/ss. from M.A. Antonov to Shaposhnikov, 1928 May 22; 133 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Note N° 0311/ss. from M.A. Antonov (at the disposal of the Chairman of the RVS USSR) to Shaposhnikov, the Chief of the Red Army Staff, with an accompanying extract from a letter from IP. Uborevichon the use of the experience of the Reichswehr for the Red Army's military technical equipment. Original.
  - Note from Voroshilov to I.V. Stalin, 1928 May 31; 134 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Note from Voroshilov to I.V. Stalin on the candidacy of the Red Army command staff who would be sent on official trips to maneuvers in Germany, and on admitting Reichswehr officers to maneuvers in the USSR. Copy.
  - Letter from I.P. Uborevich to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1928 June 18; 135 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Letter from I.P. Uborevich, the Force Commander of the MVO, from Berlin, to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the prolonging of work from May to June and on the program of trips to the field for June-August. Original.
  - Letter N° 2335 from I.P. Uborevich to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1928 July 11; 136 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Letter N° 2335 from I.P. Uborevich to K.Ye. Voroshilov on his impressions of the disciplinary policies of the German Reichswehr. Certified copy.
  - Report N°N° 044735s/s., 01418/ss. from the Chief of the 4th Directorate of the Red Army Staff to Voroshilov, 1928 July 20-25; 137 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Report N°N° 044735s/s., 01418/ss. from the Chief of the 4th Directorate of the Red Army Staff to Voroshilov on the signing of an agreement with the German firm Walter [sp], with an enclosed letter to Malinovskii, Chairman of Osoaviakhim. Original.
  - Letter from I.E. Yakir to Voroshilov, 1928 August 20; 138 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Letter from I.E. Yakir, Force Commander of the UVO, to Voroshilov on the course of studies of a group of Soviet commanders in Germany. Original. Autograph.
  - Special Summary N° 3 from the Special Department of the UVO, 1928 September 19 - November 8; 139 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Special Summary N° 3 from the Special Department of the UVO on the stay of German officers at the UVO maneuvers. Original.
  - Special Summary N° 4, 1928 September 19; 140 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Special Summary N° 4 from the Special Department of the UVO on the stay at the UVO maneuvers of foreign officers, including those from the Reichswehr. N° 2977. Original.
  - Cipher telegram N° 822 from I.S. Unshlikht to K.Ye Voroshilov, 1928 November 13; 141 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Cipher telegram N° 822 from I.S. Unshlikht to K.Ye Voroshilov on the approval of candidates for study at the Berlin Military Academy. Certified copy.
  - Letter N°087508 from General Groner to Voroshilov, 1928 December 9; 142 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Letter N°087508 from General Groner to Voroshilov on the removal of obstacles between the Reichswehr ministry and Metakhim in the delivery of ammunition. Copy.
  - Basic proposals and conditions on the buying airplanes from Heinkel, 1928 December 14; 143 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Basic proposals and conditions of a report given by Ya.I. Alksnis, Dep. Chief of the VVS of the Red Army, at a meeting of the RVS USSR on the buying of airplanes from the German firm Heinkel. Original.
  - Extract from a protocol of a meeting of the RVS USSR, 1928 December 14; 144 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Extract from a protocol of a meeting of the RVS USSR on a report by Ye.I. Alksnis; with a resolution on the purchase of airplanes from the German firm Heinkel. Original and copy.
  - Purchase of Heinkel ND 37 fighter airplanes, 1928 December 14; 145 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Information from the Directorate of Affairs of the NKVM and the RVS on the purchase of Heinkel ND 37 fighter airplanes. Original.
  - Report from Ya.K. Berzin to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1928 December 24; 146 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Report from Ya.K. Berzin to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the collaboration between the Red Army and the Reichswehr. Original.
  - Exchange of commanders from the Red Army and the German Reichswehr, 1928; 147 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Instructions on the exchange of commanders from the Red Army and the German Reichswehr, sent to Voroshilov. Original.
  - Report N° 1/ss. from I.A. Khalepskii to K. Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 January 3; 148 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Report N° 1/ss. from lA. Khalepskii, the Chief of the Directorate of Mechanization and Motorization of the Red Army Staff to K. Ye. Voroshilov on [his] official trip to Germany. Original.
  - Letter from Berlin from A.I. Kork to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 January 21; 149 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Letter from Berlin from A.I. Kork, military attache in Germany, to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the stay in Germany of Soviet specialists and commanders of the Red Army. Autograph.
  - Letter from I.E.Yakir to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 January 26; 150 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Letter from I.E.Yakir to K.Ye. Voroshilov on his stay in Germany. Autograph.
  - Reports from A.I. Kork to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 February 4 - 18; 151 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Reports from A.I. Kork to K.Ye. Voroshilov. Typewritten with resolution of K. Voroshilov.
  - Report N° 65/20ss. from Ya.M. Fishman to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 February 10; 152 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Report N° 65/20ss. from Ya.M. Fishman, Chief of the Military Chemical Directorate of the Red Army, to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the results of an official trip by officials of the directorate to Germany. Original.
  - Draft report from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo I.V. Stalin, 1929 March; 153 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Draft report from K.Ye. Voroshilov to the Politburo I.V. Stalin concerning a proposed sending of personnel by the German Reichswehr. Resolution of S.S. Kamenev. Copy.
  - Memorandum N° 2292/55 from Shleifer to I.S. Unshlikht, 1929 April 10; 154 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Memorandum N° 2292/55 from Shleifer, member of the board of the Narkomat of Trade of the USSR, to I.S. Unshlikht on the requests of the Narkomvoenmor [Voroshilov] for Heinkel airplanes and BMW motors. Original.
  - Conclusion of the Military Department on proposals from Krupp, 1929 April 18; 155 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Conclusion of the Military Department on proposals from Krupp. Resolution of B.M. Shaposhnikov. Copy.
  - Memorandum N° 65/25ss. from Ya.M. Fishman to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 April 19; 156 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Memorandum N° 65/25ss. from Ya.M. Fishman to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the preparation for the forthcoming arrival of a groups of German specialists for chemical tests. Original.
  - Letter from A.I. Kork to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 April 22; 157 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Letter from A.I. Kork to K.Ye. Voroshilov on his trip to a metallurgical factory. Original.
  - Report N° 028605/ss. from B.M. Shaposhnikov to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 May 20 - 22; 158 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Report N° 028605/ss. from B.M. Shaposhnikov to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the forthcoming official sending of Red Army commanders to Germany for the autumn of 1929 on the objectives for this trip and on the composition of the group. Original.
  - Memorandum N° I/132s. fromI.S. Unshlikht to M.M. Litvinov, 1929 May 31; 159 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Memorandum N° I/132s. from I.S. Unshlikht to M.M. Litvinov, the NKID, with conclusions on the possible participation of German capital in the USSR's far eastern air service. Certified.
  - Record of K.Ye. Voroshilov's conversation with General Hammerstein and Colonel Kuhlental, 1929 September 5; 160 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Certified copy.
  - Dispatch from P.N. Lunev, 1929 November 30; 161 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Dispatch from P.N. Lunev on the results of talks with Professor Schmidts. Contains marginal notes by I.P. Uborevich. Certified copy.
  - Extract from protocol N° 38, 1929 December 3; 162 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Extract from protocol N° 38 of a meeting of the RVS USSR on the introduction into Red Army armaments of German motors. Copy.
  - Report from I.P. Uborevich to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 December 11; 163 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Report from I.P. Uborevich, the Chief of Red Army Armaments, to K.Ye. Voroshilov on a conversation with General Ludwig. Original.
  - Conversation of a representative of the Military Department with Niedermeyer, 1929 December 25; 164 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Extract from a conversation of a representative of the Military Department with Niedermeyer. Contains marginal notes of I. Uborevich about [his] perusal [of this]. Certified copy.
  - Letter N° 126/g. from V.K. Putna to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1929 December 26; 165 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Letter N° 126/g. from V.K. Putna, military attache in Germany, to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the invention by Professor Dornje [sp?] of an "airplane-ship" DO X. Copy.
  - List of Reichswehr officers present in the USSR during 1930, 166 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    List of Reichswehr officers present in the USSR during 1930 (drawn up by the 4th Directorate of the Red Army). Copy.
  - Expenses for trips to Germany of Red Army commanders during 1930, 167 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Copy.
  - Letter N° 3/g. from V.K. Putna to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1930 January 9; 168 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Letter N° 3/g. from V.K. Putna to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the activities of I.A. Khalepskii's commission in Germany and other questions. Original.
  - Letter to I.P. Uborevich from a German frrm (in German), 1930 January 17; 169 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Memo report N° 028909/ss. from Ya.K. Berzin to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1930 January 24; 170 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Memo report N° 028909/ss. from Ya.K. Berzin to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the necessity for regulating the pay of official representatives of the Red Army at the joint enterprises in Kazan and Lipetsk. Original with a resolution by Voroshilov.
  - Record of a conversation of Berzin with General Ludwig, 1930 January 25; 171 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Record of a conversation of Berzin with General Ludwig on the organization in the USSR of the production of anti-aircraft guns.
  - Letter from Putna to Voroshilov, 1930 January 28; 172 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Letter from Putna to Voroshilov on an inspection of a Thiell clock- and machine-building factory with the aim of organizing the production of time-fuses with a timing mechanism in the USSR. Original with a resolution by Voroshilov.
  - Memo report from R.P. Eideman to I.P. Uborevich, 1930 February 14; 173 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Memo report from R.P. Eideman to I.P. Uborevich on the course of a conversation with Colonel Mittelberger concerning the cooperation of the two armies. Certified copy.
  - Letter from V.Kh. Tairov to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1930 February 16; 174 (Box 2, Folder 6)